Why do we do 108 prostrations?
It’s nice to meet you, Sunim.
(Sunim) Yes.
While listening to your Dharma talks,
I noticed you mention
108 prostrations quite often.
I may be asking this question because
I don’t know much about Buddhism,
but I wonder if prostration is merely
a Buddhist ritual.
Why do you recommend we do 108 prostrations
if it isn’t just for physical exercise?
I don’t have a basic understanding of why
we prostration as part of our practice.
I'd like to know.
(Sunim) Yes.
Let’s say you and I are lying in bed,
and we start to argue about something.
I might shout at you
“What? That’s not right.”
If the argument became that heated,
would we continue to lie there
or would we sit up?
Please tell me
(Questioner) We would sit bolt upright.
That’s right.
What about if we were sitting in a chair
and talking and began to argue heatedly?
Would we continue to sit in the chair or
would we stand up as we became aggravated?
(Questioner) We would stand up.
Right. When we both stand up and the argument
intensifies even more, do we look up or down?
(Audience Laughter)
We look up.
Do we close our eyes or
keep them wide open?
(Audience Laughter)
Our eyes are wide open.
We might shout at each other
“What? What nonsense!”
We jump up onto our feet,
stiffen our necks,
look up and widen our eyes
This is the body language of someone who is
strongly caught up in the notion that he is right.
What does your getting upset imply?
It implies that you are right,
and the other person is wrong.
Then thoughts like,
“Oops, maybe it was my mistake”
or “Maybe I misunderstood you”
pop into your mind.
Your eyes lose their glare and
you lower your gaze and your head.
You may progress to saying,
“I’m sorry” or “it was my fault.”
What if you feel even worse
about your mistake?
You would bend your upper body and say,
“I am really sorry.”
What if you feel like the mistake
you made is unforgivable?
You would kneel down.
Then what? You would lower
your head to the floor.
This is the body’s way of expressing penance.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes, yes.
When you kneel down and
put your forehead on the floor
that is the body’s way of expressing you
completely let go of the notion that you are right.
Standing up is the way your body most strongly
expresses your ego, the idea that I am right.
So, prostration is a way to express with your body
that there is nothing to insist you are right.
When you kneel down on the floor,
you are physically expressing,
“I am sorry. I made a mistake. There was nothing
I could insist that I was right about.”
There are three benefits to prostrating
First, when you bend down and put your
forehead on the floor and then stand up again,
it exercises your whole body.
For this reason, prostration is the most
effective form of whole-body exercise.
So, if you have only twenty minutes to exercise,
prostration is the best one to choose.
First, it is beneficial physically.
Other exercises only have physical benefits
but prostration can also help you reduce stress.
Because it helps you let go of your ego,
of the notion that you are right
and this produces psychological effects.
Stress is produced
when you insist you are right.
You don’t become stressed
when you acknowledge your faults.
People in modern society deal with a lot
of stress due to their strong ego.
Prostration is beneficial as a way for people
to deal with stress in modern society.
It is still beneficial even if
you are forced to do it.
It is even better if you prostrate repeating
words that can train your mind.
This is what we call words for practice
or words for prayer.
For example,
let’s say you are anxious,
and you pray to God to
make your mind peaceful.
This is asking someone to do
a favor for you, right?
That’s not how words for practice works.
Instead, when you prostrate,
repeat “Thank you, God. I am at peace.”
Sending a message like this to your
unconscious is how it should be done.
Performing 108 prostrations repeats that
message to yourself 108 times.
Let’s say you are having issues in your
relationship with your husband.
Although the words for practice may be
different based on the situation,
let’s assume you were given the words,
“you are right. I have flaws. I am sorry”
You would be prostrating
with those words.
Usually, when your husband expresses
his opinions to you,
your automatic response to his words
is that he is wrong.
But if you continue your practice with
the practice words,
one day you will find yourself listening to
him without having an automatic judgement.
You will think “well, I can see his point”
and start simply accepting his words.
This kind of thing can happen
when you prostate.
But it doesn’t really matter if you prostrate
100 times, 103 times, or 108 times.
What do we traditionally call defilements?
We call them the 108 defilements, right?
So, we do 108 prostrations to get rid of
the 108 defilements.
I tell Christians that
if you prostrate to the Buddha,
it may be seen as worshiping an idol
which is against the Ten Commandment,
but it isn’t.
Prostrating is about repenting
your own flaws to yourself,
not praying to another God-like figure.
I don’t think prostration goes against the
principles of Christianity.
But if they insist that
it is against their principle,
I tell them to do 103 prostrations
instead.
Why 103 prostrations?
How many Christians were persecuted
when Christianity was oppressed in Korea,
and how many of those became regarded
as Christian saints by the Vatican?
Aren’t there 103 Korean saints
registered at the Vatican?
So, if you are a Christian and the 108
prostrations make you uncomfortable,
do 103 prostrations to each of the saints.
But don’t get jealous because 103 is
5 less than 108.
(Audience Laughter)
My point is that prostration doesn’t go
against whatever belief you have.
Even if you are a protestant, this does
not go against Christian beliefs.
That's how you should approach
prostration.
So, if we prostrate 10 times
the 108 prostrations?
That is 1080 prostrations.
How about 30 times?
That is 3000 prostrations.
How about 100 times 108 prostrations?
That is 10000 prostrations.
If perform 108 prostrations times 10,
that is 1080 prostrations,
but once the count passes 1080,
we don’t say 3024 prostrations, etc.
We just say 3000 prostrations.
Doing 3000 prostrations or 10000
prostrations is physically challenging.
Prostration that many times contains
an aspect of discipline.
Many people who attempt to prostrate that
many times give up in the middle.
But if you push through,
even while physically suffering,
there are many thoughts that
arise in your mind.
In the beginning you may focus on your words
for practice and repent towards your husband,
but as you become tired, other thoughts
might creep in, “what have I done wrong?”
Those thoughts drive you to feel more
resentment towards your husband.
Then you calm down and feel that
maybe it wasn’t all his fault.
Your mind changes like that numerous
times during your prostration.
This process will lead you to let go of
your notion that you are right.
As your mind softens,
you start thinking “he must have felt this
way and that’s why he acted like that,”
and you develop an understanding of where your
spouse is coming from when he acts a certain way.
When you reach this understanding
while prostrating,
you start accepting another’s point of view
and that unlocks your mind which releases stress.
For example, when you say,
“I don’t know why you behave like that,”
your voice gets higher
because you feel more stress.
“I don’t know” is also a cause for stress.
But when you come to understand someone
and say “Oh, that’s why he behaved like that,”
it releases your stress.
That shows your understanding of the other person.
That’s why we practice with words
that help us understand the other instead
of trying to be understood by them.
You get stressed when you try to
be understood by others.
When you develop an understanding of other people,
your mind becomes free from stress.
That’s why we practice prostration.
It is possible to do an autosuggestion
without performing such physical work.
While comfortably sitting, you can tell
yourself I am at peace,
but this message doesn’t get delivered to
your subconscious world easily.
However, when you prostrate,
you will sweat
and develop a feeling of resistance
toward doing the prostration,
but if you continue to prostrate despite
such difficulty, what does that mean?
You can’t continue unless you are
determined to change your karma.
That’s why we suggest doing
the 108 prostrations in the morning.
Prostrating 108 times has nothing to do
with asking God to bless you.
It has nothing to do
with any religious implications.
It is just a very effective
therapeutic tool.
To sum up: first, it’s very beneficial
for your physical health
Second, it helps you to
break down your ego.
Third, if you prostrate while
repeating words for practice,
you can make changes
to your subconscious,
which will free you
from the stresses of life.